welcome to meditating
uh with john vervicky we
uh live stream this every weekday
morning at 9 30 a.m
eastern time if you're joining us for
the first time welcome you can just
continue with us but i recommend you see
uh the description for this video you'll
find links there
previous sits and lessons you should
immediately do lesson number one
and then every you know maybe once or
twice a week
do another lesson keep meeting with us
and then you'll be
very quickly integrated into the course
and into the sangha
at the end of every lesson we have a set
and sorry at the end of every set not at
the number of lessons at the end of
every set
we have a q a and if you're going to ask
questions
uh remember there's a couple things here
please limit the questions to
anything from the entire course uh but
please
also be willing to share observations or
comments
this is helping everybody and so if we
can expand
the q a to regularly reliably include
observations and comments
uh that will help everyone in the senga
that's much appreciated
please like this stream uh to increase
its
visibility on the youtube algorithm if
you have more general questions
um every third friday of the month at 3
pm eastern time we'll be live stream on
youtube
a general q a and we just did one last
friday it was excellent
uh many people from the center were
there and from elsewhere
um so that's also something i encourage
you to participate in especially you
have more encompassing questions
okay so we're in this unusual uh format
today usually
we're it's closer in and we're zoomed in
i'm sitting on a mat
and a pillow but today we are again
um we are again doing the uh
walking meditation so
let's begin again so i'm standing side
on
and i'm going to turn
my right foot so again here's my line
perpendicular is 90 and turn my right
foot 45 degrees
and i step and i'm keeping my the
distance between my
heels this way i'm keeping it hip width
and i'm stepping as far as i could
without having to
leave or without lifting my back heel
see my right heel back there
without lifting that off the floor i'm
keeping a bend in both of my knees
and i'm getting about 70 percent of my
weight onto my front leg and 30
onto the back so and then as i
step i exhale
all right inhale and come back my foot
comes up and i turn
45 degrees for my hips okay
so inhale and then i'm going to as i
exhale i'm going to
push my weight this way and i'm going to
align my knee
so it's over the center of my foot
but not past my toes i exhale okay
inhale okay
and i bring and i'm going to turn my
hips
all the way i'm going to turn my hips
from here 45 to the right
and by turning my hip it brings my
right leg up so i'm turning 45 feet to
the left my mistake i apologize
and i'm turning 45 degrees to my left
and that is bringing i'm treating my
hips 45 degrees
and that is bringing up my right heel
again i'm keeping this hip distance
again
same length as my previous step and then
i exhale and i'm going to straighten my
hips the whole time it takes me to move
forward
keeping a bend in this leg and abandon
this leg
okay so let's do those two things
together
in the sequence so we begin 45 foot i
inhale
exhale inhale
exhale now i go back inhale
and i turn this foot out of 45 degrees
exhale
inhale exhale
okay let's do that again and then we'll
review the turning
so i'm trying to i think i'm just maybe
a little bit more over here
so 45 degrees inhale
exhale inhale
exhale inhale turning my hips you see my
hips
exhale inhale
exhale inhale exhale
okay so one more time
you're just watching my hips now see
what they're doing they've turned here
and then they turn even more
i think it's actually yeah so here
and then even more a little
past 45 degrees in fact as you're
bringing the back foot up
remember see how my foot is landing so
when my foot lands
heel to toe as my weight comes forward
like so for example
it's here heel to toe
okay so now we're going to talk about
how we turn
so first of all i'll show you straight
on how we turn
so i just want to keep on my mark sorry
i have to keep checking
make sure you're not losing my feet all
right so that
i want to end with this foot forward my
right foot
and then i pull this back and i pivot
and see how my weight is all back
also do this side on my weight comes
back i
pivot but i don't put that foot down
it's not actually touching the floor yet
okay and then i pivot even more as i
shift my weight from my left to my right
and then i bring this foot up and over
and i go forward
okay so what does that
look like side on
okay you can now i showed you one way
last time and i said only do it with one
foot i'm showing you both ways now
but if this foot is forward my left foot
is bored i come back and i pivot
and then up and over okay
so let's just do the turning here
here here
and back pivot
here back
pivot here
back pivot
stop okay now let's put the walking and
the turnings together
so exhale
this way i'm going to turn this way
because i'm running out of space
so back pivot
up and over again
and pivot this way because i'm running
out of space
so always inhale right
as you're drawing in always exhale as
you'd be expressing force
going forward
so here i'm inhale although i'm bringing
this leg up because no weight's going
forward
i'm actually drawing everything into my
right hip so that's why i'm inhaling
and then exhaling like you put force
into that
okay so
that's the foot movement that's the
breathing
what are you doing with your mind well
you are
trying to make the sensations in your
dantean
right here so like as if you were doing
the pasta you're here you're following
your breath
because the movements are tied to your
breath
and you're also right
i'm also aware i'm meditating on
you you already know how to do this but
i'm not not only meditating on my breath
here
i'm meditating on the centeredness and
rootedness
i'm really making them focal in in my
walking meditation so that while i'm
moving
i'm trying to keep that sense of being
centered and rooted
so i'm focusing obviously on the walking
itself
i'm focusing on my breath because the
breath is timed
with this steps and i'm my meditative
focus is also on my center around my
root
now that that's a lot more than normal i
get that and that's the point
but those four will be very soon very
integrated together
because when you're moving in this
fashion
right when you're moving in this fashion
being centered and rooted
is natural to it and so you you're
feeling the center and the root
that contact all the way down the
centeredness
and then you breathe it and i'm feeling
the center and the root
throughout and i'm following my breath
because the breath is timed
with the movement
okay everyone i will review all of this
again tomorrow
i review all of this again tomorrow okay
i'm just going to go off panel for a sec
and get my mat and
my meditation pillow you can be
comfortable
get seated
all right so everyone
let's get in your posture set your
phones on do not disturb
uh we will begin with a short chant and
then
we will go into the sun sitting and then
we'll have time probably for a question
or two
we will begin when i say begin
begin
[Music]
[Laughter]
one
[Music]
begin your silences
slowly begin to come out of your
practice
trying as best you can to integrate what
you've cultivated in your practice
with your everyday consciousness
cognition
character and community perhaps by
reciting the five promises to yourself
okay so let's we have time for this one
two questions or comments uh we have one
from uh human wannabe interesting uh
name there and then following the
learning process that you prescribed but
when i do it
alone it takes 25 to 30 minutes is
anything that i could do to shorten it
yes there's a shorter version of the
rooting process
that you might want to try to do which
is
uh begin with your attention awareness
here above your head
as you inhale expand your awareness as
you would in meta
as you exhale contract it as you would
in vipassana
and then in the space before you take
your in-breath drop your attention to
the center
of your skull in-breath
of breath in breath
out breath center my throat center my
chest
solar plexus
dante end
contact point
and then opening and make melting and
draining three feet
into the earth try that leave your brain
being no
uh normal don't force it don't don't
develop
ventilate try that as a
rooting process that i think you'll find
helpful for speeding things up a bit i
still think that
the three lines of uh looking at
looking loosening uh listening for
listening letting it flow and letting it
go
are are optimal uh but it in order to
uh open up more space view
i'm assuming that what you mean is that
that's kind of too much time
and so in order to open up space so that
more of your practice is for other
things
you can try that uh sort of faster
routing process
it's a it's part of the seated q con
i recommend that trying maybe one time a
week
to do the more the longer three line
version
of the rooting process
kiera kroger has an observation she
wants to share
that's great thank you kyra i'm starting
to hear members of the sangha who share
their wisdom on the discord as part of
my inner sage
yes and it deeply warms my heart and
helps me to feel
a deep sense of connection thank you for
sharing that
um that will happen more and more uh
generally
um that sangha and your inner sage
and i suppose your teacher
is that who i am um they will all merge
symbolically um and uh
that will actually improve uh the
functionality and the sense of presence
of your inner sage so that's fantastic
thank you for sharing that kira
um and that is something that
generally happens to everybody as they
are cultivating the buddha of the dharma
and the sangha
i want to thank you all for joining i
want to thank my dear friend and techno
major mar
my beloved son jason who's behind the
scenes making things work
please subscribe to this channel to be
notified of the next video there you
will find links to a lecture series
awakening for the meeting crisis
and the dialogue series voices with
raviki where many of these themes and
related themes are discussed in depth
and set into a more encompassing
framework invite others please who might
benefit
benefit from sharing this series uh
i believe brett is here mark is also
here um it's
very important to try and spend some
time on the discord server
uh there are people there who join us
for this practice they're also doing
their own sit i believe at 5 00 pm
eastern time there's all kinds of
vibrant discussion groups many of the
people from voices with rebecca come on
there for q
a i do buy weekly general q a um
so as much as possible i believe the
singer actually home
sorry that the song was actually home
yesterday on the discord server
so it's good for these two communities
to increase their mutually enriching
conversation and communion
so reminder we're doing this every
weekday morning at 9 30
eastern time remember that continuity of
practice is more important than your
quantity of practice
there is no enemy worse than your own
minded body
no friend no ally no true companion on
the path better than your mind and body
and that really sings for me when i'm
doing the walking meditation no true
companion on the path
better than your own mind and body
elapse onto yourselves and to each other
hope to see you all tomorrow take care
everyone